<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Podcast | Craig Marvelley]]></title>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/categories/podcast/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-06T11:14:02+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://marvelley.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Marvelley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Never Out of Beta Returns!]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/2014/06/09/never-out-of-beta-returns/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T14:26:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/blog/2014/06/09/never-out-of-beta-returns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love podcasts. Since I moved house and gained a commute I&rsquo;ve whiled away the time to and from work listening to <a href="http://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/">The Talk Show</a>, <a href="http://therecord.co">The Record</a>, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/football/series/footballweekly">The Guardian&rsquo;s Football Weekly</a>, and a couple of other great shows. Enough that I&rsquo;m barely able to listen to them all. They made me pine for <a href="http://www.neveroutofbeta.com">Never Out Of Beta</a> though, a podcast <a href="https://twitter.com/gavD_UK">Gav</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/handybitesize">Carey</a> started a couple of years ago that I and a few friends would guest on, which was great fun.</p>

<p>But my longing is over &ndash; Gav and I have rebooted the show, and the <a href="https://soundcloud.com/never-out-of-beta/episode-0-2-1-its-not-in-my">first episode is available now</a> via Soundcloud!</p>

<p>A couple of notes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Production &ldquo;issues&rdquo; (well, I forgot a bunch of audio equipment) meant that we had to record this one via my Macbook&rsquo;s built in microphone. It turned out ok, but we&rsquo;ve got higher standards which hopefully we&rsquo;ll get closer to next time</li>
<li>It took longer than I&rsquo;d have liked to get the episode out because I&rsquo;m learning the ropes when it comes to editing. The WWDC stuff is a bit old hat now, but get past that and I think there&rsquo;s some interesting discussion around the DevOps mindset and provisioning with Ansible</li>
<li>An iTunes feed is coming as soon as I can sort one out &ndash; I listen to podcasts through the Apple Podcast app so I&rsquo;m eager to make it available there</li>
<li>Inspired by The Talk Show&rsquo;s recent switch we&rsquo;re hosting the show on SoundCloud, which has been perfect so far</li>
</ul>


<p>As with pretty much everything else Gav and I do, it might take a few iterations before this is something we&rsquo;re really happy with, and feedback to aid us in getting there will be very much appreciated.</p>

<p>If you like tech, you might like this. Check it out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
