<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Podcast | Craig Marvelley]]></title>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/categories/podcast/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-17T09:25:28+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://marvelley.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Marvelley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NOOB 0.9.19 - 'You Shouldn't Have to Click It']]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/2014/09/17/noob-0-dot-9-19-you-shouldnt-have-to-click-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-17T10:17:41+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/blog/2014/09/17/noob-0-dot-9-19-you-shouldnt-have-to-click-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gav and myself mainly talk about software company processes and principles, with a little bit on communication tools and AWS thrown in for good measure.</p>

<p>This is the first podcast we&rsquo;ve recorded remotely, since Gav moved to Bristol. Following <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2030512/how-we-produce-our-podcasts.html">this Macworld post&rsquo;s directions</a> seemed to work; we each recorded our own audio via Quicktime, and synced it up with our &ldquo;master&rdquo; recording from Skype, made possible via <a href="http://ecamm.com/mac/callrecorder/">Call Recorder</a>. I sequenced it all in GarageBand, with the odd final edit in Audacity.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re five episodes in since we rebooted the podcast back in June. There&rsquo;s still a lot of room for improvement (especially, for me, in my speech - I find it hard to speak in a slow cadence, and concentrating on that often distracts me from the topic at hand), but I feel that each episode has gained in professionalism, and they&rsquo;re a lot of fun to do.</p>

<p>Check it out on Soundcloud <a href="https://soundcloud.com/never-out-of-beta/you-shouldnt-have-to-click-it">here</a>, or even <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/podcast/never-out-of-beta/id908946657?mt=2">subscribe on iTunes</a> thanks to Soundcloud&rsquo;s currently-in-beta integration with that service, which we&rsquo;re fortunate to have been given access to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Never Out of Beta Returns!]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/2014/06/09/never-out-of-beta-returns/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T14:26:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/blog/2014/06/09/never-out-of-beta-returns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love podcasts. Since I moved house and gained a commute I&rsquo;ve whiled away the time to and from work listening to <a href="http://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/">The Talk Show</a>, <a href="http://therecord.co">The Record</a>, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/football/series/footballweekly">The Guardian&rsquo;s Football Weekly</a>, and a couple of other great shows. Enough that I&rsquo;m barely able to listen to them all. They made me pine for <a href="http://www.neveroutofbeta.com">Never Out Of Beta</a> though, a podcast <a href="https://twitter.com/gavD_UK">Gav</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/handybitesize">Carey</a> started a couple of years ago that I and a few friends would guest on, which was great fun.</p>

<p>But my longing is over - Gav and I have rebooted the show, and the <a href="https://soundcloud.com/never-out-of-beta/episode-0-2-1-its-not-in-my">first episode is available now</a> via Soundcloud!</p>

<p>A couple of notes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Production &ldquo;issues&rdquo; (well, I forgot a bunch of audio equipment) meant that we had to record this one via my Macbook&rsquo;s built in microphone. It turned out ok, but we&rsquo;ve got higher standards which hopefully we&rsquo;ll get closer to next time</li>
<li>It took longer than I&rsquo;d have liked to get the episode out because I&rsquo;m learning the ropes when it comes to editing. The WWDC stuff is a bit old hat now, but get past that and I think there&rsquo;s some interesting discussion around the DevOps mindset and provisioning with Ansible</li>
<li>An iTunes feed is coming as soon as I can sort one out - I listen to podcasts through the Apple Podcast app so I&rsquo;m eager to make it available there</li>
<li>Inspired by The Talk Show&rsquo;s recent switch we&rsquo;re hosting the show on SoundCloud, which has been perfect so far</li>
</ul>


<p>As with pretty much everything else Gav and I do, it might take a few iterations before this is something we&rsquo;re really happy with, and feedback to aid us in getting there will be very much appreciated.</p>

<p>If you like tech, you might like this. Check it out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
