<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PHP | Craig Marvelley]]></title>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/categories/php/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-14T11:26:14+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://marvelley.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Marvelley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Including Filtered Thumbnail Data With the WordPress JSON API Plugin]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/2013/09/26/including-filtered-thumbnail-data-with-the-wordpress-json-api-plugin/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/2013/09/26/including-filtered-thumbnail-data-with-the-wordpress-json-api-plugin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/json-api/">JSON API</a> plugin is a great tool for exposing your WordPress data. I&#8217;ve used it to provide content to a few mobile applications; it&#8217;s well featured and most importantly, quite flexible. If your content providers are happiest using a CMS like WordPress, your project can benefit by allowing them to use the authoring tools they&#8217;re comfortable with while allowing you to easily access the content they&#8217;re creating, either to use directly within your application, or as I tend to do, by exporting the data into another application which then proxies the data to mobile applications. I find the latter approach gives you greater control over features like caching, while making it easier to relate the data to domain models that aren&#8217;t handled by WordPress.</p>

<p>But I digress! This post was conceived because when requesting all posts of a certain type through the plugin, response times were hideously slow. The request I was making looked like this:</p>

<p><a href="http://domain.com/?json=get_posts&amp;post_type=artist&amp;count=1000&amp;order=ASC">http://domain.com/?json=get_posts&amp;post_type=artist&amp;count=1000&amp;order=ASC</a></p>

<p>Reading the documentation for the plugin, I found that it was possible to filter the response to only contain properties that I wanted, which I figured should reduce the amount of work WordPress was having to do:</p>

<p><a href="http://domain.com/?json=get_posts&amp;post_type=artist&amp;count=2&amp;order=ASC&amp;include=id,title,content,custom_fields,thumbnail_images">http://domain.com/?json=get_posts&amp;post_type=artist&amp;count=2&amp;order=ASC&amp;include=id,title,content,custom_fields,thumbnail_images</a></p>

<p>This proved to be true, but I hit a snag when trying to include the thumbnail_images property &#8211; adding it to the CSV of whitelisted fields had no effect. Through trial and error it transpired that including the thumbnail field also has the effect of including the thumbnail, thumbnail_size, and thumbnail_images fields. The final URL ended up looking like this:</p>

<p><a href="http://domain.com/?json=get_posts&amp;post_type=artist&amp;count=2&amp;order=ASC&amp;include=id,title,content,custom_fields,thumbnail">http://domain.com/?json=get_posts&amp;post_type=artist&amp;count=2&amp;order=ASC&amp;include=id,title,content,custom_fields,thumbnail</a></p>

<p>Problem solved!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony2: JSON Responses for XHR Errors and Authentication Failures]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/2012/12/20/symfony2-json-responses-for-xhr-errors-and-authentication-failures/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/2012/12/20/symfony2-json-responses-for-xhr-errors-and-authentication-failures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been working on a Symfony2 application whose user interface is presented as a single page application that makes heavy use of JavaScript. The app sends <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XMLHttpRequest">XHR</a> requests to the Symfony2 backend API to retrieve and modify data, and it uses Symfony&#8217;s authorisation/authentication functionality to protect resources so they are only accessible to logged in users.</p>

<p>In an ideal world every request made by the application will succeed, but in reality things often go wrong; the user may have provided invalid data, their session may have expired meaning they are no longer logged in, or we may have a bug in our API code which causes a server error. With an out-of-the-box installation of Symfony2, each of these scenarios will result in the default error handler rendering a HTML page which isn&#8217;t much use to our client JavaScript application &#8211; instead we want the server to issue a JSON response to our AJAX request, complete with some contextual error details, with which we can give the user a meaningful error message.</p>

<p>I did a bit of Googling and came across a <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/8607212/symfony2-ajax-login">few</a> <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!topic/symfony-devs/WvESDBprKrU">posts</a> <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12385923/handle-errors-in-ajax-within-symfony2-controller">which</a> dealt with some of these challenges, and by putting them all together I arrived at a solution which I&#8217;ll detail here in case it&#8217;s of use to anyone else.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/craigmarvelley/symfony2-xhr-error-handling">I&#8217;ve put together a demo app</a> which hopefully illustrates everything. Have a play with it (installation instructions are in the README), then read on <img src='http://marvelley.com/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif' alt=':)' class='wp-smiley' /></p>

<p><a href="/images/posts/2012/12/Screen-Shot-2012-12-20-at-21.55.12-e1356040628744.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-341" title="The demo application" src="http://marvelley.com/images/posts/2012/12/Screen-Shot-2012-12-20-at-21.55.12-e1356040628744.png" alt="" width="600" height="398" /></a></p>

<p>The app consists of a few components:</p>

<p>Client side:</p>

<ul>
<li>A jQuery global AJAX error handler</li>
<li>A login form &#8211; I have two, a Symfony2/Twig-based HTML login page which the user is redirected to if they try to access the app without a valid session, and a JavaScript login dialog which we will display if the server rejects an AJAX request due to authentication/authorisation failure, allowing the user to reauthenticate without leaving the app</li>
</ul>


<p>Server side:</p>

<ul>
<li>An authentication failure handler</li>
<li>An authentication success handler</li>
<li>A kernel exception listener</li>
</ul>


<p>As far as the rest of the app goes, I&#8217;m using the <a href="https://github.com/FriendsOfSymfony/FOSUserBundle/blob/master/Resources/doc/index.md">FOSUserBundle</a> with a standard configuration, which supplies the rest of the auth functionality, including the HTML login page.</p>

<p>Let&#8217;s start with the server components &#8211; three classes and a bit of config:</p>

<p><noscript>
  <p></p>

<pre><code>View the code on &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/4340230"&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;.
</code></pre>

<p>  </p>
</noscript></p>

<p>The <code>XHRAuthenticationSuccessHandler</code> and <code>XHRAuthenticationFailureHandler</code> class&#8217; code is triggered when the user logs in, or fails to log in, respectively. We check to see if the original request was an AJAX (XHR) one, and if so we respond with JSON. If it&#8217;s a failure we&#8217;re dealing with, we also include the exception message to give the user some feedback &#8211; note that this is a quick solution; it might be prudent to vet the message, or to translate it. I&#8217;ve also included a &#8216;success&#8217; property which is a JavaScript convention that some frameworks (like <a href="http://www.sencha.com/products/extjs">ExtJS</a>) use to execute appropriate callbacks. Finally, we wire up these handlers with the security component in our application&#8217;s <a href="https://gist.github.com/4340230#file-security-yml">security configuration</a>.</p>

<p>The <code>XHRCoreExceptionListener</code> class code is triggered whenever a kernel exception occurs &#8211; check the <a href="https://gist.github.com/4340230#file-services-xml">service definition</a> for this listener, you&#8217;ll see we tell Symfony to call its <code>onCoreException</code> method whenever an exception event is fired. Again, we only want to act if the request that caused the exception was an AJAX one. Assuming it is, we try to work out the status code to return from the exception code &#8211; if it&#8217;s a valid HTTP code, we use that, otherwise we assume a server error (500). As before, we&#8217;re reusing the exception message to provide context &#8211; but in this case, where the exception could relate to anything in the system (like a database query) we&#8217;d really want to be cautious about exposing it to the user, so this code certainly isn&#8217;t suitable for a production environment.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s it for the server, now for the client. All the functionality is in <code>src/Acme/DemoBundle/Resources/views/Welcome/index.html.js</code>.</p>

<p>First we define a global error handler, which will be fired whenever an uncaught AJAX error occurs:</p>

<p><noscript>
  <p></p>

<pre><code>View the code on &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/4348746"&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;.
</code></pre>

<p>  </p>
</noscript></p>

<p>If the problem is that the user does not have a valid authentication token, we invite them to log in.</p>

<p><noscript>
  <p></p>

<pre><code>View the code on &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/4348760"&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;.
</code></pre>

<p>  </p>
</noscript></p>

<p>The login process is interesting &#8211; the modal login form is essentially a duplicate of the HTML one, but lacks the CSRF token which is automatically injected into the HTML form by Symfony. This helps prevent spoofing so I didn&#8217;t want to remove it, so the approach I took was to request the HTML login page, capture the value of the CSRF field in the response, then use that in a second request to actually authenticate the user. This meant I could reuse the same authentication code on the server.</p>

<p>The demo app also includes two other demonstrations &#8211; making a valid request (which will fail, and force a login, if the user does not have a valid session) and an invalid one (which displays the error message returned by the server). There&#8217;s not much to say about those, the code should be self explanatory.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s it really. The code is a little rough and ready, but hopefully it&#8217;ll give you enough to go on if you&#8217;re trying to do something similar!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony2: Managing a User Entity Role With a Form Event Subscriber]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/2012/11/10/symfony2-managing-a-user-entity-role-with-a-form-subscriber/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/2012/11/10/symfony2-managing-a-user-entity-role-with-a-form-subscriber</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m working on a Symfony2 application which makes use of roles to manage what Users of the system are able to do within the app. Symfony places no limit on the amount of roles the User can have, but in the context of my application, there are only two &#8211; a base user (ROLE_USER, in Symfony parlance), and an administrator (ROLE_ADMIN). As is Symfony custom, all users would possess the default role, but the administrator role would be granted on a per user basis. I&#8217;m using the FOSUserBundle and Doctrine, so a User&#8217;s roles are stored within an array on that User&#8217; Doctrine entity.</p>

<p>I began crafting a form (using the Symfony Form component) to manage user details. When creating forms that are bound to Doctrine I&#8217;ve generally found that I&#8217;ve needed to do little in the way of form customisation; the form component does a good job of figuring out which form fields to use based on the type of the variable it is given. So name, being a string, gets modelled as a textfield, while their registration date, being a DateTime object, causes a series of select boxes to be created which allow dates and times to be entered. So far so good.</p>

<p>But of course there has to be a reason for a blog post, and this is mine: I wanted a checkbox to toggle on/of the administrator role for each user. Since roles are stored in an array on the bound entity, the default is to render a collection of fields, which leads to an array of values being submitted by the form. Trying to modify the field definition to a &#8216;single&#8217; field, like a checkbox, led to an error as the Form component doesn&#8217;t know how to map an array to a single value. A multi-value field wasn&#8217;t an option as I didn&#8217;t want to expose the roles (which wouldn&#8217;t necessarily make sense to an end user), and I didn&#8217;t want to get into messing about with Twig templates if I could help it; a bit of Googling led me to <a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/cookbook/form/dynamic_form_generation.html">this article</a> on the cookbook, which describes how to dynamically add elements to forms using a Form event subscriber; this turned out to be just what I needed.</p>

<p>Reading through the cookbook article, the following plan took shape: when the form is created, add a checkbox to the form which is ticked depending on whether the User object bound to the form has the administrator role. When the form is submitted, if the checkbox is ticked, grant the user that role. If it is not, remove the role from their array of granted roles.</p>

<p><a href="/images/posts/2012/11/Screen-Shot-2012-11-10-at-14.51.51.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-311" title="The resulting form" src="http://marvelley.com/images/posts/2012/11/Screen-Shot-2012-11-10-at-14.51.51.png" alt="" width="793" height="491" /></a></p>

<p>To implement this, I needed two classes; a Form class, of course, and a new class that implements Symfony\Component\EventDispatcher\EventSubscriberInterface and subscribes to events on the form. As in the cookbook example, when the &#8216;preSetData&#8217; event fires I&#8217;d be adding a field to the form. In addition, when the &#8216;bind&#8217; event fires, I&#8217;d be using the value of the field to modify the bound object, in this case the User being managed. This is what I ended up with:</p>

<p><noscript>
  <p></p>

<pre><code>View the code on &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/4051034"&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;.
</code></pre>

<p>  </p>
</noscript></p>

<p>I&#8217;m manually adding the subscriber to the form in UserType::buildForm(), which feels a bit weird when the usual approach would be to define a service and tag it appropriately. I&#8217;m not sure if that&#8217;s possible with Form subscribers, that&#8217;s just how the cookbook approach went. I&#8217;d imagine there are other ways I could have achieved the same result, but I like this approach because I don&#8217;t have to modify my User class at all, and I don&#8217;t have to delve into form field customisation.</p>

<p>The only downside I&#8217;ve found so far is that there doesn&#8217;t seem to be a way to order the fields that get added in the listener &#8211; they are always placed at the start of the collection, regardless of when the subscriber is attached to the form. This means that some template work is necessary to place the field as desired.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deactivating a Macports Install of XDebug in a LAMP Environment]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/2012/09/20/deactivating-a-macports-install-of-xdebug-in-a-lamp-environment/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/2012/09/20/deactivating-a-macports-install-of-xdebug-in-a-lamp-environment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few times I&#8217;ve found myself cursing when trying to toggle <a href="http://xdebug.org/">XDebug</a> on and off via <a href="http://www.macports.org/">Macports</a>. Typically I&#8217;ll be debugging with it enabled, then disable it for development/testing to get the fastest experience possible (it tends to really impact performance on large codebases, such as a Symfony2 standard install), only to experience segfaults when I refresh the page I&#8217;m working on.</p>

<p>The solution I&#8217;ve found is when restarting Apache (which is necessary for the change to PHP&#8217;s installed modules takes effect), to use an explicit start/stop rather than a restart. <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/stopping.html">According to the Apache docs</a> restarting only kills off children processes, so the parent remains running:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sending the <code>HUP</code> or <code>restart</code> signal to the parent causes it to kill off its children like in <code>TERM</code>, but the parent doesn&#8217;t exit. It re-reads its configuration files, and re-opens any log files. Then it spawns a new set of children and continues serving hits.</p></blockquote>

<p>I imagine this leading to a discrepancy in the loaded PHP modules, which causes the issue.</p>

<p>So when wanting to toggle XDebug, I use these commands:</p>

<pre>Install (first time only):
sudo port install php5-xdebug

Disable:
sudo port deactivate php5-xdebug
sudo apachectl stop
sudo apachectl start

Enable:
sudo port activate php5-xdebug
sudo apachectl stop
sudo apachectl start</pre>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jeff Atwood Is a Muppet.]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/2012/06/30/jeff-atwood-is-a-muppet/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/2012/06/30/jeff-atwood-is-a-muppet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was having a nice, relaxing Saturday morning until I read through my Twitter timeline and was directed to Jeff Atwood&#8217;s latest post on Coding Horror, &#8220;<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2012/06/the-php-singularity.html">The PHP Singularity</a>&#8220;. After reading through it, and the comments from other readers, I got annoyed. Really annoyed.</p>

<p>I won&#8217;t repeat the article, but the gist of it is:</p>

<ul>
<li>PHP is a horrible language</li>
<li>Something must be done</li>
<li>Jeff is the person to do it</li>
</ul>


<p>I quite enjoy blogging but I don&#8217;t do it very often. I try to make sure anything I talk about is well researched, because a baseless opinion is worthless, but I don&#8217;t have a lot of free time &#8211; so if I don&#8217;t have something I consider worth saying, I don&#8217;t say it.</p>

<p>Jeff doesn&#8217;t have the same concern. You may wonder why I read his blog, given that I clearly take exception to some of its content, but the funny thing is that when talking about things he is knowledgable of, he has some great advice.</p>

<p>Like when he talks about <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2011/10/on-parenthood.html">his children</a>, because he obviously knows them, or <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2012/06/because-everyone-still-needs-a-router.html">routers</a>, where he&#8217;s clearly done some investigation. Now, I&#8217;m about to become a father, so I really enjoyed the former post, and if I needed to buy a router, I&#8217;d probably just be lazy and pick one from the latter because he knows a lot more about them than I do.</p>

<p>But here&#8217;s the thing. Jeff doesn&#8217;t seem to know much about PHP. I&#8217;d guess he&#8217;s read some posts about it, seen a few Q&amp;As on Stack Overflow about it (a site he deserves massive kudos for), read through the PHP Manual, whatever &#8211; but he&#8217;s not a PHP developer. When he says PHP is &#8216;terrible&#8217; or &#8216;deeply flawed&#8217;, I wonder how he&#8217;s come to that conclusion? Has he ever developed anything substantial in PHP? What is he basing this opinion on? He&#8217;s played with his children, he&#8217;s bought and installed a router. But when it comes to PHP, is the extent of his knowledge that which he has gleaned from others? Because if that&#8217;s the case, he really should think twice about offering his opinion on it.</p>

<p>The most glaring statement in the entire article is this one:</p>

<blockquote><p>Therefore, I&#8217;d like to submit a humble suggestion to my fellow programmers. The next time you feel the urge to write Yet Another Epic Critique of PHP, consider that:</p>

<ol>
<li>We get it already. PHP is horrible, but it&#8217;s used everywhere. Guess what? It was just as horrible in 2008. And 2005. And 2002. There&#8217;s a pattern here, but it&#8217;s subtle. You have to look very closely to see it. On second thought, never mind. You&#8217;re probably not smart enough to figure it out.</li>
<li>The best way to combat something as pervasively and institutionally awful as PHP is not to point out all its (many, many, <em>many</em>) faults, but to <strong>build compelling alternatives</strong> and <strong>make sure these alternatives are equally pervasive, as easy to set up and use as possible</strong>.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>How anyone can offer a &#8216;humble&#8217; suggestion and then go on to question the reader&#8217;s intelligence is besides the point (though it does nicely illustrate Jeff&#8217;s technique of drawing the reader in with deference only to hit them with a massive dose of self-righteousness) &#8211; but there&#8217;s two things I really take exception to here. Firstly, as <strong>anyone</strong> who has spent any real time with PHP knows, the language is far, far different now to what it was in 2002. For heaven&#8217;s sake, PHP5 (with a brand new object model that made proper OOP possible) didn&#8217;t make its debut &#8217;til 2004, and support for register_globals (one of the worst features of PHP, ever) was removed in the most recent version, 5.4. Those facts are available under <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PHP">PHP&#8217;s entry on Wikipedia</a>, but perhaps Jeff&#8217;s not smart enough to Google the history of PHP before commenting on it?</p>

<p>Secondly; assuming for a second that PHP is as horrible as he deems it to be &#8211; the best way to &#8216;combat&#8217; it isn&#8217;t to &#8216;build compelling alternatives&#8217; and &#8216;make sure these alternatives are equally pervasive, as easy to set up and use as possible&#8217; &#8211; no, the &#8216;best&#8217; thing to do (considering the amount of developers and sites worldwide who depend on the language and are getting things done with it every single day) is <strong>get involved</strong> with and <strong>actually understand</strong> PHP &#8211; read the <a href="http://news.php.net/php.internals">internals mailing list</a>, make <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc">requests for comments</a>, code contributions, etc. It&#8217;s a silly person who decides to try something new before attempting to fix what&#8217;s broken, when there is so much invested in it. Perhaps if Jeff wasn&#8217;t trying to drum up interest in this new project of his, he&#8217;d have been a little less inflammatory?</p>

<p>Look, as someone who has used PHP successfully for the last decade, obviously I&#8217;m going to disagree with Jeff&#8217;s opinion. But the language has not only helped me get a great job, a nice house, and will shortly be helping me pay for one of those baby things, it&#8217;s also made Facebook the biggest website in the world, and enabled Yahoo! to build (ok, and throw away, but it&#8217;s not PHP&#8217;s fault) an empire. When Jeff&#8217;s got off his soap box and tried to build something equally successful in PHP <strong>and failed</strong>, I&#8217;ll start taking his opinion seriously.</p>

<p>As I said, I don&#8217;t like making statements unless I&#8217;ve researched them fully. I&#8217;ve read Coding Horror for a long time, and I feel qualified to say that Jeff Atwood is a <a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=muppet&amp;defid=778738">muppet</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
