<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ios | Craig Marvelley]]></title>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/blog/categories/ios/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://marvelley.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-06T19:26:54+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://marvelley.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Marvelley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three20, XCode 4 and the Case of the Missing Header Files.]]></title>
    <link href="http://marvelley.com/2011/08/25/three20-xcode-4-and-the-case-of-the-missing-header-files/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://marvelley.com/2011/08/25/three20-xcode-4-and-the-case-of-the-missing-header-files</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a good hour of hitting my head against a brick wall, I finally managed to get Facebook&#8217;s three20 iOS library integrated with my XCode 4 based project, documented here for posterity and the hope that it may save someone else from the raw, savage agony I&#8217;m currently feeling.</p>

<p>I followed the instructions on the <a href="http://three20.info/article/2010-10-06-Adding-Three20-To-Your-Project">three20 website</a> to the letter, using the python installation script to add the library to my project, but whenever I tried to include the main Three20.h header file within my application code I got a &#8216;file not found&#8217; warning which failed the build. After much trial and error / Stack Overflow searching I came across <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6833804/problem-with-three20">this post</a> which seemed to suggest trying every header search path under the sun. Indeed, one of these finally worked &#8211; I narrowed it down to the $(BUILT_PRODUCTS_DIR)/../three20 entry, but YMMV.</p>

<p>As much as I like iOS, and XCode, Apple&#8217;s solution for integrating libraries is extremely error prone &#8211; and this was <em>with</em> a custom installation script. Hopefully once XCode 4 adoption has grown the process can be simplified, as newer libraries like <a href="http://restkit.org/">RestKit</a> seem to be less complicated to install.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
